# Inventory Management System

## Project Title
Inventory Management System – Python Mini Project

## Description
The Inventory Management System is a menu-driven Python console application designed to manage and track inventory items efficiently. The system allows users to add new items, view available inventory, search items by category, and save inventory records to a file.

This project is developed as part of the Python Mini Project assignment and follows all the guidelines provided in the assignment document.

---

## Objectives
- To understand the use of lists and dictionaries in Python
- To implement a menu-driven program using loops
- To practice functions, conditional statements, and exception handling
- To implement basic file handling operations in Python

---

## Features
- Add new inventory items
- View all inventory records
- Search inventory items by category
- Save inventory data to a text file
- Simple and user-friendly menu-driven interface

---

## Data Structure Used
- List: To store multiple inventory items
- Dictionary: Each inventory item is stored as a dictionary with the following keys:
  - ID
  - Name
  - Category
  - Quantity
  - Price

---

## Concepts Used
- Lists and list methods (append, len)
- Dictionaries and dictionary methods (get, keys)
- String methods (strip, upper, title)
- User-defined functions
- Conditional statements (if, elif, else)
- Looping (while loop)
- Exception handling (try / except)
- File handling using open()

---

## Menu Options
1. Add Item  
2. View Inventory  
3. Search Item by Category  
4. Save & Exit  

---

## File Handling
Inventory records are saved in a file named:
inventory_records.txt

---

## How to Run the Program
1. Make sure Python is installed on your system
2. Save the program file as inventory_management.py
3. Open Command Prompt / Terminal
4. Run the program using:
   python inventory_management.py
5. Follow the on-screen menu instructions

---

## Author Information
Name: ___UDAY PR_________________
Course: Python Programming
Institution: ____BNM INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY________________
Academic Year: 2024–25

---

## Conclusion
This Inventory Management System demonstrates the practical implementation of core Python concepts such as data structures, functions, loops, exception handling, and file operations. The project successfully fulfills all the requirements of the Python Mini Project assignment.

